<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://nordine.quadar.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://nordine.quadar.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/><updated>2025-06-17T14:18:49+00:00</updated><id>https://nordine.quadar.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><entry><title type="html">2025 IEEE Technology Predictions: A New Era of Digital Transformation</title><link href="https://nordine.quadar.github.io/blog/2025/IEEE-expected/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2025 IEEE Technology Predictions: A New Era of Digital Transformation"/><published>2025-01-28T15:59:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-28T15:59:00+00:00</updated><id>https://nordine.quadar.github.io/blog/2025/IEEE-expected</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://nordine.quadar.github.io/blog/2025/IEEE-expected/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2> <p>In the previous release, we explored the secure-by-design principles in IoT, following our discussion about AI-powered cybersecurity threats in the industrial IoT field. Today, we’ll examine a broader technological horizon that will shape our digital future, based on the IEEE Computer Society study involving 53 technology experts from 17 countries.</p> <p>With no surprise, AI emerges as the dominant force in technology predictions for 2025, with Large Language Model (LLM) deployment receiving the highest grade (A-). The study reveals not just incremental changes, but a fundamental transformation in how AI will integrate into our systems - from specialized AI agents to enhanced robotics, all requiring significant workforce adaptation. Particularly noteworthy is the rapid development of AI applications in critical areas like drug discovery and medical diagnostics, signaling AI’s expanding influence beyond traditional domains.</p> <p>What makes these predictions particularly relevant to our field is the emerging focus on cybersecurity. As AI systems become more prevalent, next-generation cyberwarfare (B-) and AI-security concerns take center stage, fundamentally transforming how we approach digital security - especially in IoT and industrial systems.</p> <p><em>Reference: 2025 IEEE Technology Predictions Report</em></p> <p>The IEEE study categorizes 22 breakthrough technologies into six key domains: verticals, applied AI, user interfaces, non-functional characteristics, applied computing, and energy. This visualization demonstrates how these technologies interconnect and influence each other, with AI and security concerns spanning multiple categories.</p> <h2 id="the-technology-landscape-a-paradigm-shift">The Technology Landscape: A Paradigm Shift</h2> <p>The 2025 predictions reveal three fundamental shifts that deserve our attention. First, AI is evolving from a tool to the foundation of technological advancement. The high grade for LLM deployment signals a move toward specialized, efficient AI models that can be deployed across industries. Second, we’re witnessing the convergence of digital and physical worlds through AI-enhanced robotics (B+) and drone adoption (A/B), creating smarter, more adaptive systems. Third, there’s a growing emphasis on sustainable and human-centric technology development.</p> <p><em>Reference: 2025 IEEE Technology Predictions Report</em></p> <p>This graph reveals a crucial insight: technologies with the highest potential impact on humanity often face greater implementation challenges. Note how AI-related security technologies cluster in high-impact areas, suggesting their critical role in future technological development.</p> <h2 id="breaking-down-the-key-transformations">Breaking Down the Key Transformations</h2> <p><strong>The AI Revolution Gets Real:</strong> AI is moving beyond hype to practical implementation. Specialized AI agents (A/B) promise to transform operations across finance, manufacturing, and healthcare sectors. These aren’t just automated systems; they’re intelligent collaborators that can handle complex tasks while working alongside humans.</p> <p><strong>Sustainable Technology Takes Center Stage:</strong> The emphasis on sustainable technology is evident through predictions like IT/energy convergence (B+) and nuclear-powered data centers (B/C). These trends suggest a future where computational power and environmental responsibility must coexist.</p> <p><strong>Healthcare’s Digital Transformation:</strong> Healthcare emerges as a major beneficiary of technological advancement, with AI-based medical diagnosis (B) and wearables/biomarkers (B+) promising more precise, accessible, and proactive healthcare delivery.</p> <h2 id="the-new-face-of-cyber-threats">The New Face of Cyber Threats</h2> <p>Perhaps the most concerning prediction is the evolution of cyberwarfare. Unlike traditional attacks focusing on system vulnerabilities, next-generation threats will target AI systems themselves. Attackers will employ AI to create sophisticated attacks that can manipulate other AI systems’ decision-making processes - a particularly worrying development as organizations increasingly rely on AI for critical security decisions.</p> <p>For instance, the report predicts that attackers will focus on “black box” AI models, inserting carefully crafted misleading inputs that can alter predictions in subtle but dangerous ways. As I mentioned in my previous release, this creates a new battlefield where the integrity of AI decision-making becomes the primary target.</p> <p><em>Reference: 2025 IEEE Technology Predictions Report</em></p> <p>This table highlights the critical skills needed for 2025, showing a clear trend toward integrated AI expertise. The increasing overlap between AI and security skills suggests professionals must develop hybrid competencies.</p> <h2 id="impact-on-iot-and-industrial-systems">Impact on IoT and Industrial Systems</h2> <p>These predictions have significant implications for IoT security. As AI agents become more prevalent in managing IoT systems, the security landscape becomes more complex. The good news is that AI-enhanced robotics and autonomous systems are predicted to achieve better security frameworks, particularly in industrial settings.</p> <p>However, this integration of AI in IoT systems creates new attack surfaces. Organizations will need to consider:</p> <ul> <li>AI model security alongside traditional device security</li> <li>Protection against data poisoning in IoT sensor networks</li> <li>Secure AI decision-making in autonomous systems</li> <li>Enhanced monitoring for AI-driven anomaly detection</li> </ul> <h2 id="preparing-for-the-ai-security-convergence">Preparing for the AI-Security Convergence</h2> <p>The report suggests several key areas where organizations should focus their security efforts:</p> <p><strong>AI Model Protection:</strong> Developing robust verification systems for AI model inputs and outputs.</p> <p><strong>Data Integrity:</strong> Implementing strong validation mechanisms to prevent poisoning attacks.</p> <p><strong>Security Automation:</strong> Leveraging AI agents for enhanced threat detection and response.</p> <p><strong>Human Oversight:</strong> Maintaining appropriate human supervision of AI security systems.</p> <h2 id="final-thoughts">Final Thoughts</h2> <p>The road to 2025 presents both exciting opportunities and significant challenges. While AI and automation lead the charge, the emphasis on security and human-centric design suggests a more balanced approach to technological advancement. For security professionals, this means developing new skills at the intersection of AI and cybersecurity while ensuring robust implementation practices. For organizations, the preparation for these changes while maintaining strong security practices will be essential to be best positioned for success in this rapidly evolving environment.</p> <p>Stay tuned for our next release, where we’ll dive deeper into specific security implications of these emerging technologies and how organizations can prepare for them.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="AI-Technology"/><category term="AI"/><category term="LLM"/><category term="Cybersecurity"/><category term="IoT"/><category term="IndustrialSecurity"/><category term="DigitalTransformation"/><category term="TechPredictions"/><category term="IEEE"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Exploring the IEEE Computer Society's technology predictions for 2025, with AI leading digital transformation and emerging cybersecurity challenges]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Is Secure-by-Design the Key to IoT Cybersecurity?</title><link href="https://nordine.quadar.github.io/blog/2024/Secure-by-Design/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Is Secure-by-Design the Key to IoT Cybersecurity?"/><published>2024-09-05T15:59:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-05T15:59:00+00:00</updated><id>https://nordine.quadar.github.io/blog/2024/Secure-by-Design</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://nordine.quadar.github.io/blog/2024/Secure-by-Design/"><![CDATA[<p>In my previous release, we explored the battleground of AI-powered cybersecurity threats in the industrial IoT (IIoT) field. We discussed how AI can play a major role in both sides of the game, either as defender and attacker. In this release, we are slightly shifting our focus to another critical aspect and hot topic of IoT security: Secure-by-Design (SbD). Could this be the key to truly secure IoT devices from the ground up?</p> <h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2> <p>As our world becomes increasingly connected, with more than 16 billion devices already in use and integrated into our daily lives and industries and a total of 40 billion to be connected by 2030, the need for robust security has never been more pressing. From personal data and intellectual property to national security, the risks introduced by vulnerable IoT devices are significant and growing very fast. In this article, I want to dive into this concept that might just be the answer to many of these challenges.</p> <p>The first question one may ask is what Secure-by-design is! Actually, this is not a novel concept. Its roots trace back to the early days of computer security around 1970. However, its application to IoT is making it a hot topic these days. The Cybersecurity and Infrastructure Security Agency (CISA) defines it as “technology products built in a way that reasonably protects against malicious cyber actors successfully gaining access to devices, data, and connected infrastructure”. In simple words, Secure-by-Design is a concept that prioritizes security from the very beginning of the design process. Instead of developing security features after a product is launched either due to breaches or internally found vulnerabilities, SbD embeds these features into the core architecture of the device or system in a proactive fashion. Think of it like building a castle with walls, gates, and all defenses planned from the blueprint stage, rather than adding these elements after the structure is already built. According to a report published by the National Institute of Standards and Technology (NIST), this approach is essential because it will help reducing vulnerabilities by addressing them during the design phase and in all steps of the development lifecycle. By integrating security practices in early stages, developers can avoid risks such as memory safety issues, which have historically posed big issues to software systems.</p> <h2 id="why-secure-by-design-is-important-for-iot">Why Secure-by-Design is important for IoT?</h2> <p>IoT devices are more vulnerable to cyberattacks because of their interconnected nature and often with limited security measures either due to their hardware limited resources or related cost. As these devices emerge and get into critical applications, securing them becomes an important task. The risks are not just theoretical; they are real and growing and every day we witness new exploits using vulnerabilities in these devices. Consider the infamous Mirai botnet attack, which exploited vulnerable IoT devices to launch a massive distributed denial-of-service (DDoS) attack, shutting down websites and services globally. Another significant incident occurred in 2022 when the Russian threat actor group known as “APT44/Sandworm” targeted critical infrastructure in Ukraine. According to one of Google’s Threat Intelligence report, the attackers gained unauthorized access to a supervisory control and data acquisition (SCADA) system, subsequently manipulating the victim’s substation circuit breakers. This malicious action resulted in disabling the power grids across major regions of Ukraine.</p> <p>Incorporating secure-by-design principles in IoT development can address possible vulnerabilities in advance. For instance, using memory-safe programming languages is one way to prevent common attacks like buffer overflows. These languages, such as Rust, are designed to avoid many of the pitfalls that lead to vulnerabilities in traditional languages like C and C++. Moreover, SbD could be extended beyond software. It also includes hardware-based security features, such as secure boot processes, which ensure that only trusted software can run on a device. This is particularly important in IoT, where devices are often deployed in diverse and sometimes hostile environments.</p> <h2 id="best-practices-for-secure-by-design-in-iot">Best Practices for Secure-by-Design in IoT</h2> <p>In April 2023, the CISA, along with the NSA, FBI, and international partners from countries including Australia, Canada, the UK, and Japan, issued a complete guidelines on secure-by-design principles. This guidance, updated in October 2023, calls for technology providers to take greater ownership of their products’ security, shifting the responsibility away from consumers and small organizations. Their report, “Shifting the Balance of Cybersecurity Risk: Principles and Approaches for Security-by-Design and Default,” outlines three core principles:</p> <p>Take ownership of customer security outcomes: Technology manufacturers must prioritize the security of their products through the entire lifecycle, from conception to deployment . Embrace radical transparency and accountability: Companies should openly share information about their security practices, vulnerabilities, and improvements. This includes publishing detailed statistics and trends about product security. Lead from the top: Security must be elevated to a core business priority, led by executive-level commitment and integrated into the organizational culture and vision. To put these principles into practice, an organization may require a multi-faceted approach that included the following actions:</p> <p>Implementing security-centric culture by establishing regular meetings with executive leadership to drive the importance of secure-by-design. Create policies that reward teams for developing secure products. Implementing threat modeling during the development process of a system or software to identify and correct potential vulnerabilities proactively. Adopting secure coding practices by prioritizing the use of memory-safe programming languages like Rust. Google, for instance, has reported that up to 70% of their security vulnerabilities were due to memory safety issues. Incorporating hardware-based security by using secure boot processes and hardware security modules (HSMs) to ensure device integrity. Implementing continuous automated security testing throughout the development process, including static and dynamic analysis tools. Enhancing secure-by-default configurations with features like multi-factor authentication enabled by default and at no additional cost. Implementing continuous monitoring and updates. Companies like Fortinet are leading the way in implementing these principles. Their approach includes rigorous internal code testing and analysis, active threat hunting, proactive communication about vulnerabilities, and incorporation of industry-recognized best practices. For instance, Fortinet’s Secure Product Development Lifecycle Policy (SPDLC) ensures that security is built into each product from inception, covering every stage of the product life cycle. Other industry leaders are already embracing SbD principles:</p> <p>Google’s Android: By transitioning to memory-safe languages, Google has effectively eliminated entire classes of vulnerabilities in Android. Bosch’s CISS: The Connected Industrial Sensor Solution incorporates a secure element chip for cryptographic operations, protecting against both physical and cyber attacks. Medical IoT: Companies like Medtronic are implementing built-in secure communication protocols in implantable devices, safeguarding against potentially life-threatening hacks.</p> <h2 id="challenges-and-considerations">Challenges and Considerations</h2> <p>Of course, implementing secure-by-design doesn’t come without challenges. It requires to change the mindset and put more commitment from manufacturers to make security as one of the main priorities from the beginning. Additionally, there are many technical challenges, such as ensuring that secure design practices are scalable and applicable to the wide type and requirements of IoT devices on the market. Another significant challenge is the need for standardization. Without clear and universally adopted standards, it can be difficult to ensure that all IoT devices meet a minimum security baseline. More challenges are still valid and need to be addressed, such as:</p> <p>Balancing security and usability: Stringent security measures may impact user experience, requiring a delicate balance. Resource constraints: Smaller manufacturers may struggle with the initial investment required for comprehensive security measures. Legacy systems: adding modern security features to existing and old IoT devices can be technically challenging and sometimes economically unfeasible. Evolving threats: The rapidly changing nature of cyber-threats requires constant vigilance and adaptation as attackers develop new techniques and add more challenges. The last consideration I would like to mention, other than the technical ones, is the economic implications of this concept. While it requires initial investment and may extend development timelines, the long-term benefits are substantial.</p> <h2 id="looking-forward">Looking Forward:</h2> <p>Looking ahead, the integration of AI and ML into SbD practices promises to further enhance IoT security. These tools could enable more advances threat modeling and automated security testing, helping to identify and mitigate vulnerabilities more effectively and proactively.</p> <p>So, is secure-by-design the key to IoT cybersecurity? I believe it’s a critical piece of the solution. By integrating security from the very beginning, we can build IoT systems with already good foundations from a security perspective.</p> <p>In conclusion, secure-by-design is not just a best practice or some principles that should be followed; it’s becoming an essential strategy for surviving and improving in an increasingly connected and vulnerable digital landscape. As technology providers take more responsibility for the security of their products from the early development stages, we can say that we move closer to a future where IoT devices enhance our lives without compromising public safety and privacy.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Cybersecurity"/><category term="IoTSecurity"/><category term="SecureByDesign"/><category term="Cybersecurity"/><category term="InternetOfThings"/><category term="TechInnovation"/><category term="CISA"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Secure-by-Design concept and guidlines]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The AI Battleground: Protecting Industrial IoT from Advanced Cyberattacks</title><link href="https://nordine.quadar.github.io/blog/2024/role-of-ai/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The AI Battleground: Protecting Industrial IoT from Advanced Cyberattacks"/><published>2024-05-27T15:59:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-27T15:59:00+00:00</updated><id>https://nordine.quadar.github.io/blog/2024/role-of-ai</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://nordine.quadar.github.io/blog/2024/role-of-ai/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2> <p>The IIoT is becoming the backbone of modern industries as it drives high levels of efficiency, connectivity and innovation to the field. However, this technology brings new cyber threat surfaces as the number of connected device is keep increasing and expected to reach 29 billion by 2027. With cybercrime costs expected to hit $10.5 trillion USD by 2025, the battle between AI-powered cybersecurity and AI-enhanced cyberattacks has taken center stage in the industrial sector.</p> <p>IIoT environments now witness cyber threats at increasing rates, from network-based attacks like Denial of Service (DoS) and Man-in-the-Middle (MitM) to malware, exploit, and social engineering. The utilization of AI to develop more sophisticated attack methodologies includes AI-powered botnets that adapt to avoid detection, intelligent malware that explores and exploits vulnerabilities independently, and socially engineered attacks augmented with AI that could deceive even vigilant employees. In addition, vulnerable communication protocols, legacy devices, and lack of security standards put IIoT systems at very high risk. The repercussions of these breaches can be devastating from compromising critical infrastructures and supply chains to public safety.</p> <h2 id="ai-the-defender-and-the-attacker">AI: The Defender and the Attacker</h2> <p>The continuous evolution of threats has urged cybersecurity researchers and industry experts to take AI as an important tool for combating cyberattacks. Researchers are mainly using Machine Learning and Deep Learning techniques to go through huge data volumes, detect anomalies, and detect threats in real time. These techniques can learn from previous incidents, adapt to new patterns of attacks, and provide predictive insights to prevent future breaches.</p> <p>For example, ML-based intrusion detection systems can monitor network traffic, identify suspicious activities, and raise alerts for response. DL models could analyze malware samples, learn the characteristics of the malware, and generate signatures to detect and block them. Natural Language Processing (NLP) can be used for log analysis, detection of social engineering, and insider threat identification.</p> <p>However, AI doesn’t just remain a defense tool; on the other hand, it is being weaponized by cybercriminals. Adversarial attacks are one of the most serious challenges posed by bad actors who manipulate AI models for the purpose of deceiving and circumventing security systems. A slight perturbation in input data is enough to misclassify threats into benign classes that go undetected by the ML models. Further, AI-driven password guessing, smart jamming, and autonomous hacking are advancing rapidly and increasingly making traditional security measures difficult to cope with.</p> <h2 id="ongoing-challenges-and-future-directions">Ongoing Challenges and Future Directions</h2> <p>Despite the potential of AI in enhancing IIoT cybersecurity, there are many problems that remain. The first, and perhaps biggest, is how well ML and DL models generalize to real-world settings, where data often tends to be noisy and incomplete. Another critical aspect is the security of AI models, since they can be attacked by adversarial attacks, data poisoning, and model stealing.</p> <p>Different approaches are being researched to address these challenges. Being investigated for their potential in enhancing privacy and security, techniques developed in federated learning (FL) allow multiple parties to train models collaboratively without sharing raw data. Techniques like Moving Target Defense (MTD) and Software-Deﬁned Perimeter (SDP) are being used for creating dynamic and adaptive security architectures capable of resisting such attacks. Another critical area of research is adversarial machine learning, involving an understanding of the vulnerabilities of AI models to sophisticated adversarial attacks and mitigating these by adversarial training, defensive distillation, and robustness certification.</p> <p>Researchers are adopting Explainable AI (XAI) techniques like feature attribution, rule extraction, and counterfactual explanations to enable the improvement of the interpretability and trustworthiness of AI-powered cybersecurity systems. Graph neural networks (GNNs) are being researched as ways to capture the relational information of IIoT networks for tasks including anomaly detection, risk evaluation, and attack path prediction. Another promising approach is the integration of Zero Trust Architecture (ZTA) with AI in IIoT environments, thus enabling access control mechanisms to be more adaptive and precise. Homomorphic encryption (HE) is being researched in order to enable secure and privacy-preserving processing of sensitive data for reducing the risk of data breaches and unauthorized access.</p> <p>Reinforcement learning (RL) has already been applied to the development of adaptive and autonomous cybersecurity systems, whose defense strategies learn to change over time. Another concept under investigation is the Digital Twins that is, virtual replicas of physical assets, processes, or systems to create more accurate and predictive models of IIoT systems and thereby offer proactive cybersecurity measures and risk assessment. Moreover, blockchain technology infused with AI provides promising directions toward secure and transparent sharing of data, identity management, and access control in IIoT. Lastly, quantum computing, through its capability to resolve complex optimization problems, is now being explored in developing more efficient and robust AI algorithms for cybersecurity.</p> <h2 id="looking-ahead">Looking Ahead</h2> <p>The field of AI-driven cybersecurity continuously undergoes changes and therefore organizations should proactively and flexibly adapt to this reality. Investing in AI-powered defense mechanisms, adopting the culture of security awareness, and collaboration with industry partners and government bodies are the most necessary steps to be taken to stay ahead of the curve.</p> <p>Furthermore, developing standards, frameworks, and best practices for AI in IIoT cybersecurity is critical to guarantee interoperability, reliability, and trust. Governments and regulatory bodies have an important role in setting guidelines, encouraging research and innovation, and providing international cooperation to address the global nature of cyber threats.</p> <p>The battle between AI-powered cybersecurity and AI-enabled cyber attacks on industry environment is far from over and it’s just the beginning. This complex, dynamic landscape must be put into perspective: AI is not a silver bullet; it is a strong tool that must be used not only with care but also with responsibility and with full understanding of its implications. Leveraging the power of AI for good can actually build a secure, resilient, and prosperous future for industry and beyond.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="AI-Cybersecurity"/><category term="IoT"/><category term="IIoT"/><category term="Cybersecurity"/><category term="AI"/><category term="MachineLearning"/><category term="IndustrialSecurity"/><category term="IndustryInsights"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Role of AI in IIoT cybersecurity]]></summary></entry></feed>